Welcome to this lesson on multiplication and division
with decimals. In this session, we will learn
how to multiply two decimal numbers together.
We will also look at how to divide by a
decimal number by transforming the calculation into one involving integers.
We'll start by reviewing some key terms:
the decimal point and decimal places.
The number system is extended by using decimal
numbers to represent fractions. The decimal point separates
the whole-number part from the fractional part.
Take the number 25.374, for example. To the left of
the decimal point, we have 2 Tens and 5 Units.
To the right, we have 3 Tenths, 7 Hundredths, and 4 Thousandths.
We use this every day with money. £36.67 is simply 3 tens,
6 units, 6 tenths—which are 10 pence coins—and 7 hundredths—which are pennies.
When we talk about 'decimal places,' we are referring to the
positions of the digits to the right of the decimal point.
For instance, 79.4 has one digit after the
point, so it has one decimal place.
6.83 has two digits after the point, so it has two decimal places.
And 0.526 has three decimal places. Knowing this is crucial
for rounding and for checking our answers in multiplication.
Often, you will need to round a decimal
number to a specific number of decimal places.
Here is the method: Start at the decimal point and count
along to the required number of places. Then, look at the
very next digit—the first one you are going to remove.
If that digit is less than 5, you
simply remove it and all following digits.
If that digit is 5 or more, you must round up. Add 1 to
the digit in the previous decimal place, and then remove the unwanted digits.
Let's practice this with some examples. First,
round 5.852 to 2 decimal places.
The second decimal digit is 5. The next digit is 2,
which is less than 5. So, we leave it as 5.85.
Second, round 7.156 to 2 decimal places.
The second digit is 5, but the next digit is 6. Since 6 is 5
or more, we round up the 5 to a 6. The answer is 7.16.
Third, round 0.274 to 1 decimal place.
The first digit is 2. The next is 7, which
is high enough to round up. So, 0.2 becomes 0.3.
Finally, 15.3518 to 1 decimal place. The next digit is 5, so
we round up the 3 to a 4. The result is 15.4.
Now, let's look at multiplying two decimal numbers. The easiest way
to do this is to temporarily forget about the decimal points.
First, multiply each decimal by a power of 10—like
10, 100, or 1000—to turn them into whole numbers.
Second, multiply those whole numbers together.
Third, multiply the powers of 10 you used in step one.
Finally, divide your result by that combined power of 10
to put the decimal point back in the correct place.
Let's calculate 3.42 multiplied by 2.7.
First, we make them whole numbers. 3.42 has two decimal
places, so we multiply by 100 to get 342.
2.7 has one decimal place, so we multiply by 10 to get 27.
Now we calculate 342 times 27.
Using long multiplication, we get 9,234.
We multiplied by 100 and then by 10. 100 times 10 is 1,000.
So, we must divide our answer, 9,234, by 1,000. This
moves the decimal point three places to the left.
The final answer is 9.234.
Dividing by a decimal number can be tricky. The best strategy is to
change the problem so you are dividing by a whole number instead.
Look at the divisor—the number you are dividing by. Decide what you
need to multiply it by to make it a whole number.
Then, multiply BOTH parts of the division by that same amount. This
keeps the answer the same, but makes the calculation much easier.
Let's try 42 divided by 0.2.
We are dividing by 0.2. To make 0.2 a
whole number, we need to multiply it by 10.
So, we must also multiply 42 by 10.
The calculation changes from 42 divided by 0.2... to 420 divided by 2.
420 divided by 2 is easy: it is 210.
So, 42 divided by 0.2 is 210.
Now a harder one: 19.8 divided by 0.55.
The divisor is 0.55. To make this a
whole number, we need to multiply by 100.
So we multiply 19.8 by 100 as well, which gives us 1,980.
Our new problem is 1,980 divided by 55. We
can use long division or repeated subtraction here.
20 times 55 is 1,100. Subtracting that from 1,980 leaves 880.
8 times 55 is 440. We can subtract
that twice to clear the remaining 880.
20 plus 8 plus 8 equals 36. So, 19.8 divided by 0.55 is 36.
To summarize, we've seen that decimals are
just another way to represent fractions.
When rounding, always look at the digit immediately
to the right of your target place.
For multiplication, treat them as whole numbers first, then
put the decimal point back at the end.
And for division, always adjust the problem so
you are dividing by a whole number.
With these methods, you can handle
any decimal calculation with confidence.