Welcome to the first section of your GCSE Maths course. Number.
This section covers the fundamental building blocks of mathematics. Whether you're
managing household finances, planning a project, or just want to feel
more confident with figures, the skills we will cover here are
essential. In this brief introduction, we'll outline what you can expect
to learn and why these skills are so valuable.
In this section, we will guide you through several key topics.
We'll start by ensuring you are comfortable calculating
with both whole numbers—which we call integers—and decimals.
We will look at how to round numbers,
which is a crucial skill for estimation.
You'll explore the properties of numbers, including factors, multiples,
and prime numbers, as well as squares and cubes.
We will also cover how to find the
Lowest Common Multiple and Highest Common Factor,
and finally, we'll master the rules for working with negative numbers.
Before we begin, it's helpful to know where we're starting from.
You should already be familiar with the four basic
operations: addition, subtraction, multiplication, and division using integers.
You should also have some recognition of what multiples, factors,
and prime numbers are, even if you need a refresher.
Familiarity with the order of operations—often remembered by
the acronym BIDMAS or BODMAS—will also be beneficial,
along with the ability to substitute
numbers into simple algebraic expressions.
If any of these sound daunting, don't worry; we
will build up your understanding as we go.
Mathematics isn't just about exams; it's a vital
tool for the workplace and daily life.
Consider a cashier who needs to give the correct change, or a
delivery driver planning the most efficient route to save fuel and time.
Pilots use maths to calculate fuel requirements and
navigation, while doctors must calculate precise medicine dosages
based on a patient's age and weight.
One of the most important skills you'll develop is knowing when
an estimation is sufficient and when an exact answer is required.
To summarize, this section is designed to make
you competent and confident in basic number skills.
We will focus not just on the abstract rules, but on how
to apply them to identify and solve problems in real-life situations.
This preparation is key for the world of work
and for the rest of your mathematical journey.
When you are ready, move on to the next lesson, where
we will start applying these skills to solve real-life problems.